Stanford University
All right, so last quarter we
studied classical mechanics.
And classical mechanics is fairly
intuitive.
The basic ideas are things that you can
visualize.
You can picture in your head motion of
particles, motion of objects.
It gets a little hard when you start
thinking of
10 particles all at the same time.
Uh
but nevertheless
the whole thing is
based on um
concepts
that are drawn from pretty much the
everyday world. Of course, it gets more
and more abstract as you go along. The
crazy French who were obsessed with
elegance kept making it more and more
and more mathematically elegant.
Lagrangians
Poisson brackets, blah blah blah.
Turned out all to be tremendously
important.
Uh
the abstractions though are not all that
difficult to understand. And the basic
concept
is the concept of updating. Well, before
that, the concept of a space of states.
What is a state of a system?
Uh even before that, the concept of a
system.
A closed isolated system
that doesn't interact with anything
and whose motion and whose evolution,
whose history you wish to predict.
Classical mechanics is predictive.
It's
deterministic.
And the first concept as I said, after
the concept of a system
is the concept of the state of a system.
Uh systems can have a collection of
different states. We talked about some
very simple examples
the first day of the quarter last time.
I just described for you the most
elementary simple systems consisting of
nothing more for example than a coin.
Heads and tails. The only states of the
system are heads and tails.
They form a mathematical set.
The states.
Two of them for heads and tails, two
points one space.
Two states.
And uh we can draw them as dots.
This one stands for heads, this one
stands for tails.
And uh
you know, it's it's easy to picture in
your head.
From there, we talked about
equations of motion. Equations of motion
or laws of evolution. For the simple
very simple system of a couple of points
heads, tails
we formulated some very very simple
possible laws of motion. The simplest
being nothing happens. If you start with
heads, you stay heads heads heads heads
heads.
If you start with tails, you stay tails
tails tails tails tails.
That was a very simple law of motion.
A more complicated law of motion
if
you begin with heads, you go to tails.
If you begin with tails, you go to
heads. If you
and just oscillate back and forth.
The basic idea is the idea of updating.
If you know everything there is to know
about a system at an instant of time,
then classical mechanic everything that
there is
uh to know essentially means everything
that's needed in order to predict the
future.
If you know everything that needs to be
known, then classical mechanics consists
of a set of equations which tells you
how to update the state
given its value at any given time how to
go from one time to the next.
Uh
that basic idea for example
Well, I don't think I need to describe
the examples again. We described them at
length last time.
Uh
And that's extremely intuitive.
In going from these very simple discrete
examples to a world of continuous
motion, indeed we have to abstract. We
have to replace the idea of a small
number of states, a small finite number
of configurations
by an infinite number of configurations.
For example, the motion of a particle
along a line
uh we have to label the states by the
points along a line as well as their
velocities.
And so it does get more complicated, but
nevertheless classical physics consists
of equations which tell you how to
update the state at any given time. And
it's completely deterministic.
And as I said, easy to visualize or at
least by comparison easy to visualize
because it makes use of concepts from
the ordinary world which your brain is
rather hardwired to be able to
to understand.
Now, I always give a little sermon at
this point and I'm going to give it
again. Probably you've heard it a dozen
times.
Uh
about
the way
one has to think about physics beyond
classical physics when you move past
classical physics. I don't think it can
be said enough and it's so rarely said
that I think I will say it again.
And it's that once physics moves past
the realm of parameters that has to do
with ordinary experience
either
objects which are so small that they're
far beyond what ordinary physics is
about or velocities which are so fast
that they're far beyond ordinary
velocities whenever we move
out of the range of parameters that
we're familiar with from ordinary
experience
we inevitably
run into things that we cannot
visualize.
Nobody can visualize the motion of an
electron.
It's you're just not wired for it.
Nobody can visualize four-dimensional
space or four-dimensional space-time.
Uh
let alone
10 or 11 dimensions.
It's not the way
physics is done.
Now,
I I often read some of the stuff that
goes back and forth between some people
I suspect people in this class
about trying to explain to themselves,
to each others, uh to ask questions of
each other
about
uh certain abstract physical questions.
And I I I notice very much that a lot of
the mistakes, a lot of the confusion
happens because of trying to visualize
things using the old old-fashioned or
standard
intuitions that you're hardwired for.
You may think that physicists, good
physicists are especially good at
visualizing these things. They're not. I
cannot visualize five, six, seven
dimensions any better than you can.
But I know how to use abstract
mathematics to describe it.
There's no substitute. There really is
no substitute for the process of
abstracting
and using mathematics to describe the
things which are beyond your ability to
directly visualize.
The example that I always give and I'm
going to I'm going to do it again
tonight. I just want you to really focus
on it and realize that you're not going
to understand quantum mechanics by
trying to visualize it as some funny
form of classical mechanics. Won't work.
You'll always get it wrong.
Uh but just the idea of visualizing
space of dimensions different than three
dimensions.
In particular, I always used to say,
"Okay, how many people here can
visualize five dimensions?" And
everybody would say, "No, we can't." Of
course, there was a few fakers, a few
clowns in the class who would say,
"Yeah, I can do it. I can do it." But
they couldn't and they know they
couldn't. They can't visualize five
dimensions.
Uh
but then I began to realize also
you probably heard this before
that it's equally hard to directly
visualize two dimensions. And so I would
say to the class, "Okay, how many people
now can visualize two dimensions?" And
nobody almost everybody would raise
their hands.
And I would say, "No, you're wrong.
Close your eyes. Try to visualize two
dimensions." And they would say, "Okay,
I see it. I see two-dimensional curved
space."
What they're seeing is not
two-dimensional curved space. What
they're seeing is a two-dimensional
surface embedded in three dimensions.
Even try to see one-dimensional space.
One-dimensional abstract one-dimensional
space is just a line. You cannot see
that line in your head without seeing it
as a line drawn in a plane and the plane
you can't see without seeing it as
embedded in three dimensions. What's
going on? Why can't you?
I hate to tell you this, but you're
prisoners of your own neural
architecture.
Your neural architecture was built for
three dimensions.
All right, how do you get around it?
Well, you don't get around it by
training yourself to see four or five
six dimensions.
You get around it by training yourself
to think abstractly about it.
Okay, if three-dimensional space is a
point X, Y, and Z, then four-dimensional
space is X, Y, Z, and W. And you learn
to manipulate the symbols. Now, that's
not to say that after a while you don't
start to gain a new kind of intuition
for things. You do.
But the intuition is not the process of
physical visualization of the same kind
as when you visualize
a wave as a wave in the ocean.
Uh
So,
I warn you about that.
And I will tell you quantum mechanics is
about as abstract as anything can be.
Uh well, perhaps it's perhaps things are
even getting a little more abstract now.
But again, quantum mechanics is about
things
that
your evolutionarily developed neural
structure is not prepared to deal with
directly. Now, how do you deal with it?
Abstract mathematics again.
And
relativity, it's also true of
relativity.
It's worse in quantum mechanics.
Okay, let's uh
Let's begin
with quantum mechanics at the very very
simplest most primitive question you can
ask.
What is the state? Well, I I think we
can ask the most primitive question
is what is a system?
Now, I don't think I can answer it. It's
uh it's a sort of
undefinable. You start with the idea of
a system.
Uh and I don't think I will try to give
it a definition.
But in particular, closed system, a
closed system is one which at least
temporarily is not in interaction with
anything else. It's isolated.
It is not interacting with anything
else.
And so, it can be described by itself
as a lonesome entity with nothing else
involved.
Um
in classical mechanics
or let's
it's it's even it's not even a question
of classical mechanics.
It's a question of classical logic. The
logic the whole logic of quantum
mechanics is different than the logic of
classical mechanics.
The logic of classical mechanics again
begins of course with a system which I
won't try to describe. But the next step
is the space of states, the collection
of possible states of a system.
If the system is a discrete system like
a coin or die
die, you know, the six-sided the
six-faced die
it can have six states.
Of course, a real die, a real genuine
die in three-dimensional space of course
can be in all sorts of orientations. It
has infinitely many states. But what I
mean by a die now is I mean an abstract
mathematical die which whose states just
consist of one of six numbers.
The
space of states
is a set.
1 2 3 4 5 6. This is the space of state
of a die.
This is the space of states of a coin.
Now, the again, an abstract coin which
only has two states, heads or tails.
This would be heads, this would be
tails.
Uh the abstract space of a point
particle moving along a line, what is
that? Anybody know what that is?
What's the abstract space
of a particle
moving along a line?
Well, I'll remind you that the term is
phase space.
The space consists of the set of
possible positions of the particles and
the possible momenta.
The possible velocities.
And so, for a particle moving on a line
the possible states of the system
form a plane
and the plane
has a position, sometimes called Q a
momentum, sometimes called P.
And every point on that plane is a
possible
state of the point particle moving along
the line. But it's a set. In this case,
it's a continuously infinite set
of two dimensions. In this case, it just
consists of two points. In this case, it
consists of six points.
And uh
we can now start building some logical
concepts for classical physics.
For example
concepts such as or and and
what do they mean?
Um
or and and are concepts which apply to
collections of states.
Let's
consider a proposition.
Proposition such and such.
Uh the proposition could be
that the die
is located has a value which is even.
Is even valued.
Okay?
That's a subset of the space of states.
In fact, it consists of three of them if
I'm not mistaken.
Three odd, one, three, and five. Yes.
And another proposition would be the die
is odd. No, did I say odd? I think odd
even whatever the other whatever the
other possibility is.
That's another non-overlapping
set of
configurations.
Let's take another case. Let's take two
propositions, one of which again is that
the die is odd.
And the other proposition is that the
die
is less than or equal to three.
All right, so let's see.
Uh
Here's one
three
five, here's two
four
six
and less than or equal to three
is this set over here.
So now they're overlapping sets.
And we can ask for concepts like and and
or.
For example, the proposition
that it is that the die is both less
than or equal to three
and odd
is the intersection of these two
subsets.
One and three is odd and less than or
equal to three. So, there's a concept
of
and.
And
that it's
in this subset and in this subset
the mathematical
um
concept is the intersection of two sets.
Is the intersection of two sets, so the
sets
which satisfies both things. And that's
the concept of and.
Given two propositions, each proposition
is a collection
of states.
The concept of and
is intersection.
What about the concept of or?
Or becomes the concept of union. What
what set of states here either
is less than or equal to three
or odd?
It's the inclusive or, incidentally.
Inclusive or means it can be both.
All right, that's not the intersection
of the two sets.
It's the union of the two sets. The
union meaning everything in both sets.
Everything in here
is
either less than or equal to three
or it is odd inclusively with both being
allowed. So, the inclusive or translates
into the union and the and the
concept of and is the intersection of
sets.
That's the logic of classical reasoning
to a large extent.
Um
Here's a concept.
Two sets are completely non-overlapping.
This one and that one.
That simply means the and statement is
false. There are no states in there for
which both things are true.
Well, that's So, there's a whole logic
that is connected
with the space of states being a set.
And it's the logic of set theory. We're
not going to do the logic of set theory.
But uh
it's important for me to tell you right
now that the logic of quantum mechanics
is different. It is not based on the
idea that the state of a system is a
set.
The state of a system is something
entirely different.
And only in certain limits
only in certain limits where systems
behave classically
does whatever a space of states of
quantum mechanics, whatever it is, does
it approximately reduce to the concept
of a mathematical set.
In fact, just to tell you what it is,
it's a vector space.
And we'll talk about that.
All right, but before we do, before we
start to
um
talk about the abstract mathematics of
vector spaces
and and spaces of states of quantum
systems,
let's uh talk about experiments
and describe the simplest possible
system in quantum mechanics.
It's the coin of quantum mechanics.
The system with two states,
heads and tails.
We have to completely erase the
blackboard and start over again.
So, we have some system.
And whenever we measure that system,
whenever we measure something or other
about that system,
namely the analog of whether it's heads
or tails, we either get heads or tails.
All right, let's uh give that a um
mathematical
notation.
I'm not going to call it a coin. I'm
going to call it a qubit.
A qubit is a system which can have two
states.
And Q stands for quantum.
The
analog for classical physics is called a
c-bit, classical bit, and it is simply
the idea of a coin, heads or tails.
We're going to see that a qubit is a
much more interesting
uh
well, complicated for sure, but a much
richer idea, even though it only has in
some sense two states.
Okay, so the qubit.
The qubit, when it's measured, we're
going to talk about measuring in a
moment, is either heads or tails.
But let's describe it another way. Let's
give it a degree of freedom, a
mathematical degree of freedom, and I'm
going to call that mathematical degree
of freedom sigma.
Sigma is a traditional name
for a
for the degree of freedom describing a
qubit.
And sigma can either have take on the
value one or it can take on the value
minus one.
It's one
when the qubit is heads,
and it's minus one when the qubit is
tails.
And there's no more content in it to do
with heads and tails, but it allows us
to start being able to write equations
for something.
We can also describe this another way,
by a picture.
I'm going to describe sigma equals one
by an arrow pointing up, and sigma
equals minus one by an arrow pointing
down. No implication here of anything
geometric for the moment. Just a
notation, notation, three different
notations, heads or tails,
sigma equals one or sigma equals minus
one,
and arrow pointing up and arrow pointing
down.
Okay, now let's imagine an experiment.
An experiment involves more than just a
system.
It involves a second system, and the
second system is called the apparatus.
In classical mechanics, we never bother
thinking too much about the details,
uh unless we happen to be experimental
physicists and really going to go into
the laboratory and doing this doing an
experiment, we sort of don't worry very
worry very much about uh
uh
at least in a deep sense.
We think the system can be described
completely without ever worrying about
how you detect it, how you measure it,
or anything else.
But in quantum mechanics,
one cannot get away ignoring the concept
of a
appara- apparatus.
So, let's introduce an apparatus.
And I'll tell you what an appara- I'm
we're going to make a mathematically
abstract apparatus. I'm not going to
tell you how it works. It's a black box.
It's a black box. We're going to call it
A.
A for apparatus.
It's a box and it has a little window.
Here's the window.
It also
it really is a box. It's like a carton.
It's like the carton you get in the mail
which says this side up.
This side up.
You want it to stand upright.
Okay?
Here's a little window. By a window, I
mean a little screen, and numbers appear
on that screen.
And it has some sort of uh detector
on the end of a wire that uh that uh
senses that senses the qubit.
And it senses whether the qubit is plus
one or minus one.
So, you start with your qubit,
and you don't know what state it's in.
The experiment is to determine what
state it's in.
So, the qubit begins
in the unknown
not the unknown state, but unknown. We
don't know whether it's one or minus
one.
And we're going to do an experiment. The
experiment, and as I said, I'm not going
to tell you how they how they detector
works. It's not important for us. It's
only important that detectors do exist.
And we're going to we will talk later
about the process of detection,
but not for now.
So, it has a a sensor over here. Bring
the sensor over to the qubit.
And what does it do? A number lights up
in here,
either plus one Oh, first of all, let's
start. Before we do the detection,
the apparatus is in the neutral state,
the blank state.
No number there at all. So, let's just
call that the blank configuration of the
apparatus.
We take the apparatus over close enough
to the qubit to interact with it.
And if it's a good faithful apparatus,
it will then register a number here, and
that number will either be plus one or
minus one.
Plus one or minus one, depending on
which way
whether it was heads or tails.
That's the act of measurement.
Now, you may or may not be there to look
at the apparatus. This is a secondary.
The apparatus has detected and recorded
what is going on here.
So, that's that's something that um
in classical mechanics, of course, we do
the same thing.
There's nothing particularly quantum
mechanical about this,
but we tend never to think about it in
formulating the basic principles of
quantum mechanic- classical mechanics.
Okay, so that's an experiment
that measures
the state of or measures whether sigma
is plus one or minus one.
But we can also think of it as another
way. We can think of it not so much as a
measurement, but as a preparation,
a preparation of the system.
Here's the idea.
Supposing we in fact do measure sigma to
be plus one.
Supposing that's the outcome of the
experiment, then we can erase
the one that it wasn't,
and start over. And then say, let's
let's
back off,
reset
the apparatus, reset it means start it
over in the blank state,
and then
redo the experiment again.
Let's say we do it uh fast enough so
that there wasn't much time for anything
else to happen,
what happens? What happens
is
that the detector records again,
and if it's a good detector, and the
system hasn't had a chance to change
very much, it will simply record the
same number again. It will confirm the
previous experiment. This is important
that experiments can be confirmed.
Again, no difference between classical
and quantum mechanics in this respect.
We just emphasize it in quantum
mechanics.
Experiments can be confirmed.
We can then do it again and again and
again and again,
and we will continue to get the same
answer that we got in the first place.
So, we can say it a little bit
differently. The first experiment,
instead of saying
that it
determined
whether it was heads or tails, we can
say it prepared it in a state which was
in this case heads.
After the first detection,
it's now known to be heads. It has been
prepared in the state heads.
We can do the experiment over and over
and over again, and always get the same
answer.
All right, so
uh device that measures is also a device
that prepares a system in a given state.
Of course, the same thing would be true
had the device
determined in the first round that sigma
was minus one, then it would continue to
the to detect the same thing.
Of course, there can be bad detectors.
Not all detectors are well made, and not
all detectors work the way you want them
to work.
In which case, it just wasn't a good
detector. It didn't do what you wanted
it to do.
What does heads and tails have to do
with anything?
I don't get this point. But what's the
purpose of having a heads and a tails?
There's just two possibilities.
You want to know You want to know what
actually has to do with a head and a
tail?
There's just two possibilities.
I just used that for familiarity.
I'm not really meaning to use heads and
tails.
Okay. Now we're going to do something
new. We're going to do a new experiment.
First, we're going to start with a
preparation.
The preparation
determined
that the spin was
or a spin. I call it a spin. I'm giving
away
It is a spin. The qubit is in the state
plus one.
All right? So, the qubit
in the other notation is an arrow
pointing up. We've prepared it. We now
know We can do it a few times to check.
But once we check it, we now know that
this qubit is up and if we continue to
do it, we will continue to get the same
answer. But now we're going to do
something funny.
After we've determined or prepared the
qubit, we're now going to take the
detector and turn it over.
A
I don't know.
This side up.
We've turned the detector over.
And now
we're going to probe
the qubit again.
And what do we learn in this case?
We discover
that instead of getting plus one, we get
minus one.
By turning the detector over, we get the
opposite answer.
What is this telling us?
What is this telling us about the nature
of
this system?
What it's telling us
Oh, and of course then if we if we
take our upside down detector and
continue to do the experiment over and
over, we'll continue to get minus one.
Of course, what happens if after we do
it 35 times, we determine we we turn the
detector back upright?
Then we get plus one.
What we are learning is that whatever
this system is
this particular qubit has a sense of
directionality to it.
That when I drew it as up versus down
there really was a sense
in which orientation is being
distinguished. By turning the detector
upside down, I interchange up and down.
Well, that's what I normally mean by up
and down. Turn it over.
Look at it upside down
and it changes the sign of the qubit.
That's an indication that the qubit has
some directionality in space. Spatial
directionality associated with it. Now,
not all qubits do have spatial
directionality associated with them. But
by doing this experiment, we discovered
that whatever this qubit is, it really
does have a sense of orientation and
upness and a downness to it in space.
So, that's a piece of interesting
information.
We might begin to suspect that it's a
vector.
We might begin to suspect that since it
has a directionality in space
it's a vector.
When it's pointing up, it's different
than when it's pointing down.
We can make Well, yes. All right. So,
that's that's the basic idea of a qubit
which also happens to have a sense of
directionality. It's like this
like this pin
and our detector, when we measure it,
either measures it up or measures it
down.
But now we're going to do something
else.
Or we might Here's what we might
believe. Here's what we might believe.
Given that the detector has an
orientation to it, and it does have an
orientation to it, there's a right side
up and a wrong side up.
In fact, in the detector, we might even
think that there's something
which is itself an orientation
something built into the detector which
has an orientation in it.
And you know what we might think? We
might think that this detector is
detecting the value of the component of
a vector
along the direction
of the detector itself.
So
when a detector is right side up and it
detects this thing here, it's detecting
the component of some vector
in the plus direction. When you turn the
detector over it's measuring the
component of the same object except with
respect to an axis which has been
flipped. So, you might might start to
think this thing is a vector, this
qubit.
Okay. So, now we do something say, all
right, let's let's do something else
now. Let's turn the detector on its
side. Let's turn the detector on its
side.
We have initially
determined that the qubit was up.
We've definitely made sure it's up.
We've done it a thousand times
with the right side up detector and we
know for sure it's up. It's not down.
Yeah.
And now we detect take the sideways
detector.
Uh A, this side up over here.
With its internal arrow pointing in this
direction over here.
And what should we expect ordinarily?
Ordinarily, we would say, well
if this thing is going to measure now
not the vertical component of some
vector, but the horizontal component of
some vector.
We know that that vector was pointing
upward by the initial preparation. What
should you get here?
Well, what's the component of this
vector along the horizontal axis?
Zero. So, the answer is we should get
zero. If this were classical physics and
this were a classical little vector,
that's exactly what we would get.
So, we go and do the experiment.
Probe it
and we get
not zero, but either one or minus one
again.
Which one do we get? One or minus one?
One and minus one sort of seem to be
symmetrically located relative to the
axis of the detector.
So, I say, all right, we got I got one.
Let's do this experiment a whole bunch
of times. Let's go back.
Let's go back. Get us a new qubit. Throw
this qubit away. We're finished with it.
Get us a new qubit.
Make sure that it's pointing up and do
the same experiment again.
Well, we might get plus one again. But
again and again, we might get minus one.
We do it many, many times, exactly the
same experiment
with a qubit known to be pointing up and
we measure what we would have liked to
think was the horizontal component of
it. And we always get plus one or minus
one.
Randomly.
Randomly, but in such a way that if you
do it a great many times, then the
average value
is zero.
As many zero as many plus ones as minus
ones.
So, you do it a great many times
and you find every single one of them
is either plus one or minus one
but on the average, it adds up to zero.
You said you threw the qubit away. What
if you kept the qubit and looked at it
again?
Well, if you reoriented it if you
reoriented it and made sure it was up
again, then it wouldn't matter whether
it was a new qubit or not.
at the same qubit with the sideways and
you look at it
Okay. So, great. Good question. All
right, good. Good. Good. So, let's go
back.
Good question. We started with a qubit
known to be up.
We made a detection and we got plus one.
The implication of that is the qubit
is lying in the horizontal direction.
Somehow somehow we've detected
a plus one, but a plus one relative to a
new axis. Not the original axis, but a
new axis.
Supposing we now take that same qubit
don't modify it, but do the same
experiment over and over and over again.
We will always get the same plus one.
With All right.
Once that qubit has registered plus one
and we don't disturb it do the
experiment again and again, we will
continue to get plus one. In other
words, we will confirm we will confirm
the experiment.
Yeah.
Difference between the two
actions that you
projected from going from
top side to the bottom side. That's 180
degrees flat, whereas the other is only
a 90 degree better.
When I turn the detector by 90 degrees,
I no longer have definiteness about the
answer. The answer is random,
but only the first time. Once I do it,
once I do it and I determine
whether the horizontal component is plus
one or minus one,
then it's determined and if I do the
same horizontal experiment over and over
again, I will continue to get the same
answer.
Okay.
Well, then I could come back
and say, "Okay, now having done that and
been pretty sure
that the horizontal component of it
is in the plus direction, I can come
back and turn my detector again.
Guess what will happen?
I will find a random result.
Half the times plus, half the times
minus,
but again,
once it's determined and I do it over
and over and over again, it stays the
same. Yeah.
This is probably not important, but on
your sideways
uh detector,
your arrows are I think going the wrong
way.
How so? Uh
they point from A
Oh, oh, oh, you
Maybe this was an A here. Yeah.
This side
Ah, I think you're I don't know. All
right.
You're right.
Yeah.
That's interesting. Okay.
So that therefore I have after having
done this experiment
and found out
that I get a plus one,
I do it over and over and over a few
times, I get a plus one each time.
Let's say then I take the detector and
turn it around by 180 degrees. What do I
get?
Minus one.
But what happens if I only determine by
90 degrees?
Random.
All right, but what random
means
a particular kind of randomness, equal
probability for up and down.
All right, equal probability for plus
for plus one or minus one.
And that means that if I were to
do the same experiment, the whole thing
over and over,
uh
perhaps with a whole bunch of different
qubits.
I have a whole I have a whole reservoir
of qubits over here, lots of them. I
don't I don't even know what direction
they're are
they're in, whatever they're doing.
And I take them one at a time, I subject
them to the first experiment.
If I get up, I keep them.
If I get down, I throw them in the
trash.
At the end of the day, what I've gotten
myself is a whole bunch of qubits known
to be pointing up.
Now I take one of them
and subject it to the sideways
experiment.
I may get one or I may get one minus
one.
Yeah, I record what I got.
Throw it away.
Go to the next one, do the same
experiment. I may get plus one, minus
one, record what I get.
Take this whole collection, large
collection of them,
and do the sideways experiment for all
of them. What will be the average
result?
Zero.
Zero. I will have
as many plus ones as minus ones.
And so the average will be zero.
Let's write that in this case here by
saying
that the average value, we need a symbol
for the average value, but after this
experiment here, we will discover that
the average value
of the X of the horizontal component
of the qubit here is zero.
Classically,
if we would have created a little vector
in the up direction and we measure the
horizontal component, we simply get
zero.
In the real world, in the real world of
quantum mechanics, we always get plus or
minus one, but in such a way that the
average
is zero.
Is that true even if you don't throw
away the ones that were measured to be
minus one?
Yeah, actually it's still it's still
true. Yeah, that is that's correct.
Yeah.
Yeah, the answer's yes. Yeah.
In your description, either the detector
or the qubit seems to have some type of
memory to it.
Some type of
Yeah, we're assuming that's right. We're
assuming
that
uh that
the
law of motion of the qubit is that
nothing happens to it, so it remembers
when you when you detect it
and then you detect it again instantly
after, it hasn't changed.
Right, that's correct. Right. Now, later
on, we're going to consider
possibilities where during the
intervening time between measurements,
some interesting thing may happen. But
at the moment, we're supposing nothing
interesting happens in between. It's the
analog of the classical coin whose law
of physics was just nothing happens.
We don't talk about collapsing of a a
wave function.
That's the pulse that's going on, but uh
But no, let's not talk about that yet.
Let's talk about the operational things
that
we might do
to discover the laws of quantum
mechanics and then
then we'll put some words on them
such as collapse of the wave packet.
Okay.
So things are funny.
In some average sense,
the horizontal component of something is
zero, but in each individual
instance, you only get plus one or minus
one.
Now, let's go a little further.
Let's
Oh, incidentally, the same thing would
be true if instead of turning the
detector this way, we determine we
turned it this way,
so that the internal vector was pointing
outward. It's still be true. Same thing.
Okay, now let's do a little different
experiment.
Same setup
to begin with,
but instead of rotating the detector by
90 degrees,
let's rotate it by 45 degrees, in fact,
any angle.
Let's not do 45 degrees.
Let's rotate it by an arbitrary angle,
so that the internal detector
orientation
is now characterized by some angle theta
relative to the vertical.
So,
it's been rotated by angle theta
and do the same experiment now.
We take the first qubit,
subject it now to the um
uh
to the detector oriented at angle theta.
What do we get?
Plus one or minus one.
Do it again, what do we get? Plus one or
minus one.
What do we get? Do it again. Plus one or
minus one. Never anything in between,
but in this case, the average value
of the
experimental value
of what comes out here
is not equal to zero.
It's equal to What do you expect it to
be equal to?
Cosine of theta.
Cosine of the angle. Exactly like the X
component of a vector would be or
exactly like uh yes,
exactly like
the component of this vector along the
detector axis. The component of this
vector along the the the detector axis
would be smaller
by amount cosine theta classically.
Quantum mechanically,
we simply get plus one, minus one, plus
one, plus one, minus one, plus, plus,
plus, whatever,
uh in such a way as to average
to the cosine of the angle.
As the detector gets more and more
upright,
cosine theta gets closer and closer to
one,
and that just means it gets closer and
closer
to the value to the uh to the dis to to
the answer if the detector were
perfectly upright.
Now and then, you might get
a minus sign, but mostly plus signs. And
as soon as the detector gets perfectly
right side up, all plus ones.
What about when the detector is almost
upside down?
Well, then you get mostly minus ones,
but here and there are plus ones.
And so, it seems that the average values
of
sigma are behaving as if sigma was the
component of a vector.
This is
something, you know, really different.
This is because you prepared these as
ups. If you just took raw qubits, you'd
get
uh
If you did If you did zero, right?
If you took what? I mean, the data is
only because you started with Yes. the
ups. Yes.
Uh-huh.
Yes, that's correct. Why do we need a
collection of qubits? Why do we need
what? A collection of qubits. Since
nothing is happening to the qubit, why
can't you take the same one again and
again? No.
If you take the same one and do it over
and over again with the same detector,
you'll just get the same answer over and
over.
You'll just confirm
the previous
measurement.
So, if you take one qubit
known to be up because you made it You
You know that it's up.
And you subject it to this angularly
distorted angularly rotated experiment,
you'll either get plus one or minus one.
But if you do it the second time,
you'll just get the same answer you got
the first time.
You won't learn anything new.
Incidentally, if that weren't the case,
there would be no way to confirm
that the answer that you got the first
time was in any sense the right answer.
The only way that you confirm that the
answer is right is by checking it.
And uh one way to check it
is just
you know
If I close my eyes and I look at I mean,
I look at you and I see you upright,
and then I close my eyes again
and look at you again, I've confirmed
that the first time you were upright.
But the other one is also prepared in
the same state.
Say again. The other one is also
prepared in the down state.
This one? Yeah, second one?
Yeah.
What I'm saying is if you only have one
of them,
then only then you do the experiment,
you either get plus one or minus one.
And then if you do the same experiment
again on the same one over and over, you
just get plus one.
But
if you have a sequence of them and you
do the experiment with a sequence of
them, all having been prepared the same
way,
then you'll get a uh a statistical
distribution. Yeah. So, if you turn off
the detector and turn it on again, will
it still have a memory of the same view?
Mhm.
Switch it off, switch it off. That's
what I mean by measuring it again.
Switch the detector off and do it back
and turn it back on. So, does the
detector seem to store memory of The
detector has an orientation to it and uh
and when I say you turn
it know you changed or did not change
the unit?
Change the qubit.
Say again.
How does it know you changed or did not
change the qubit?
No, it knows that it didn't change the
that you didn't change the detector.
No, but if you switch the qubit and now
it's reset. But if you don't switch the
the qubit,
it gives you the same reading.
It already knows.
It knows.
It gives the same It gives There was
only one qubit. You did the same
Isn't it I mean, the the the detector
isn't remembering anything. It's just
the qubit that's changed. I have both
the students in the audience. Some of
them are sitting upside down, some of
them are sitting right side up.
If I randomly open my eyes at a student,
50% is standing up right side up or not.
Close my eyes, look at another student,
50% right or wrong. But if I if I open
my eyes and then close them and then
open them and close them and look at the
same student, it's always the same way.
How do my eyes know that the student was
going to
that I wasn't looking at a different
student?
The answer is I just looked at the same
student.
Okay?
So,
the whole thing is not that weird that
we can't keep track and remember which
of these things that we're looking at.
Yeah. So So, basically, we can think of
it as the act of observing
uh causes you to prepare that particular
qubit. So, once you observe that one,
you prepared it. Yeah. So, now you're
always going to get that answer. Until
you intervene by Something else. doing
something else.
If If
If you change qubits but leave the the
measuring apparatus in the same
position, Yeah. you'll you'll still get
plus one?
Okay, so that's what we're going to do
now?
Well, you're you're not you're not going
to change the orientation of the
measuring device,
but you just measure a sequence of
different qubits. Are they always going
to be up, you know, plus one or minus
one? It depends. It depends on how they
were prepared.
Somebody might have given you a sequence
of qubits which happened to be up down
up down up down up down.
You might have gotten them from
someplace. You got them from
uh
you know, from a qubit store where they
weren't where they didn't have good
quality control.
But if all of these qubits were prepared
the same way
and identical way,
and then you send them through here,
they will continue to be identical.
Right.
Um
Okay, so what this is telling us is
there's something funny
about the notion of the state of a
system. It's not as clear-cut and not as
simple as the state of either
a
coin which is either heads or tails,
or a little vector which has components
in different directions. But for
example, when you measure the component
along an axis perpendicular
to the known direction of the vector,
you get zero. Not so. So, there's
something There's something
intrinsically different
uh and the difference does trace
to the big difference between the notion
of a state in quantum mechanics and a
state in classical mechanics. Let's say
one point.
But you had here uh everything up plus
one.
And then one by one you turned it and
some were plus one and some were minus
one.
And that each one you bring up that
which was minus one
then becomes minus one back on the
original.
If you do the experiment Say again. If
If you uh
You bring one down and let's say that it
is minus one down here. Okay.
Then you turn the
uh apparatus up again.
And now you said it will be minus one
from now on. No, no, not if you turn the
apparatus.
If you turn Once you turn the apparatus
If you turn the apparatus I thought you
said if you turn the apparatus up
that if it had measured minus when it
was turned, that it would stay minus
when you turn the apparatus up again.
No.
When you turn the apparatus,
then you get a statistical distribution.
Okay? When you turn the apparatus.
Once you have
the qubit that comes out of this
apparatus,
let's say it was plus one. Let's say it
came out plus one.
And now you take that qubit over here
and you turn the apparatus back up
again,
then you're going to get a random
plus or minus.
Then it'll be random when you turn it
back up. Yeah. So, in that way then
uh Every time you turn it,
it'll be random.
You'll end up with a random bunch of
qubits. Yeah.
Yeah.
Now, it depends on the angle. If the
angle is not too large, if the angle is
small, then mostly you'll get plusses.
Right, mostly you'll get plusses.
You you postulated
a two-state system and then a detector.
But what would be the difference in
arguing saying your your signal was a
variable because your detector is a
two-state system that you
seems like you get the same output.
Say again. Say again. You You postulated
a a two-state system, plus or minus one.
Yes. But then you have a detector that
always produces plus or minus one. If
you postulated a variable to start with,
your detector seems like it would still
be a view of your
The detector would still be one.
You're It seems like you're
you're really saying your detector is a
two-state system that you can orient and
it doesn't seem to imply that Yeah.
Right. state was Uh no, no, you're
absolutely right that at some point we
have to come back to this and state say
the detector is a system
and it has states
and understand the combined system as a
quantum system
composed out of two quantum systems.
But let's let's not do that yet. Let's
divide the
and systems and then come back later and
say, "Look, a detector really is a
system and we have to be able to
describe it quantum mechanically
also as a system and to understand the
entire thing
as the
interplay between two quantum systems."
But that would take a that That will
take some
some steps before we get there.
What if the change the
What is the what? What if we change the
axis of rotation, does it matter?
You mean if we rotate this way instead
of Yeah, no, it doesn't matter.
I mean, if we do one rotation in one
using one axis and then different axis.
Yeah.
Uh
Right.
You're right. You're right in guessing
that the whole story is much more
complex,
but still um
The story is more complex, but not
inconsistent with what I said. So, don't
try to guess too far ahead.
Don't try to guess too far ahead. Let's
take the simple version of it first and
then we'll eventually come to a much
more rich understanding of it. So, for
now is it correct to think of the
detector as something that could
potentially return a continuous value
from +1 to -1, but the system will only
be
the cubit will only be measured as it
For now, yes. Right. Right. If you like,
you may think of
Yes, for now we may think of the
detector as a thing which can be
oriented in any direction and when we
measure it, it behaves like a classical
system. Yeah.
Eventually, we'll have to reconcile that
with the idea that detectors themselves
are quantum systems.
Uh
and uh have to respect the same laws as
the systems themselves.
Okay.
Okay. Now, let's
I leave you the I leave you with that to
ponder now
and we're going to
separate from this for a while and
discuss mathematics. We're going to
discuss the mathematics
of the state space or the space of
states
of a quantum system.
And as I said, it's not a set. It is not
a set in the same sense that the set of
configurations of a die is a is a set of
six configurations. It's more
complicated.
All right, but we need some mathematics.
We need some mathematics. We need some
abstract mathematics.
And the mathematics
As I said, it's not the mathematics of
set theory, it's the mathematics of
vector spaces.
Now, let's just
discuss the word vector for a moment.
You're familiar, of course, with the
idea of a vector.
A vector is an arrow pointing in a
certain direction in ordinary space.
And that's one concept of a vector, but
there's a more abstract notion of a
mathematical vector space and
mathematical vector spaces can encompass
many, many kinds of mathematical objects
which are not necessarily pointers along
a axis in space.
I generally
when we get to this point, I generally
make a new name, a non-conventional name
that nobody else that I know of uses for
the notion of an ordinary vector in
ordinary space.
In other words, a thing pointing in
ordinary space. I call it a pointer to
distinguish it from the abstract
mathematical concept of a vector.
And we're going to talk now about the
abstract mathematical concept of a
vector.
Don't think of it as pointing in
three-dimensional space, ordinary
three-dimensional space.
We'll discuss in what space it points.
All right.
All right, so let's
talk about vector spaces.
A vector space is a collection of
mathematical objects, just like numbers
are a collection of mathematical
objects.
And numbers, just the real number axis,
for example, is a vector space. It's a
special case of a vector space. It's a
one-dimensional vector space.
Complex numbers are two-dimensional
vector spaces.
All right, we're going to be talking
about vector spaces of for the moment
unknown dimensionality
and we're just going to write down a
mathematical notation
for an object in the vector space.
And as I said, vector space is now just
a name for a collection of mathematical
objects.
Completely abstract.
A is a vector.
And that's the notation for an abstract
vector.
It's Dirac's notation.
And it consists of a vertical line,
a crooked line, and a letter in between
and that stands for the vector A,
whatever the vector A is.
What can you do with vectors?
Well, you can add them.
I'm not going to tell you how to add
them. I'm just going to tell you that
given any two vectors A and B, you can
form their sum.
And their sum is another vector. Let's
call that other vector
the vector C.
So, a vector space consists of a
collection of objects which can be
added.
And numbers. And I'm sorry, I'm confused
vector versus vector space. A vector
space is a collection of vectors.
Right.
A vector space is a collection of
vectors.
The same distinction between number and
numbers.
Numbers are all the numbers.
Number is a specific number.
Okay. So, as I said, numbers are a
special case of this. You can add them.
Okay.
You can do something else with numbers.
You can multiply them by other numbers.
Well, you
Eventually, we will talk about
multiplying vectors, but not yet.
What we can do is multiply
vectors by numbers, ordinary numbers or
complex numbers and we're going to be
thinking about complex numbers.
I hope everybody is comfortable with
complex numbers.
If not,
you got to quickly get up to speed on
complex numbers.
But we don't think we don't need to know
too much.
You need to know
that a complex number is a combination
of a real number and an imaginary number
and how to multiply, add
complex numbers and you need the notion
of complex conjugate. How many people
here are familiar with the concept of
complex conjugate?
Most people, right? Almost everybody.
So, I'm not going to go in it now,
but basically for every complex number,
there is another complex number which is
its complex conjugate.
It's a mapping between numbers and their
complex conjugates. That's an important
notion.
Keep it in mind
because it's going to come back. But for
the moment,
ordinary vectors. Let's go back to oil
you know, pointers, pointers in space.
Ordinary pointers, you can multiply by
ordinary numbers,
positive or negative.
A pointer which is of a certain length
in that direction, if you multiply it by
two, it's just twice as long in the same
direction.
Multiply it by minus one, it just
becomes in the same direction except in
the opposite that well, you know, in the
opposite direction.
So, yes, you can multiply vectors by
numbers.
And in a complex vector space, we're now
going to talk about complex vector
spaces, you can multiply
vectors by complex numbers. Now, do not
try to picture this in your head as any
kind of pointer in some direction.
Just accept we're now talking about a
mathematical abstraction
where a vector, any given vector,
can be multiplied by any complex number.
I'm going to use Let's see, what shall I
use for complex number? Uh
I In my notes, I used C, but I don't
want to use C.
Z.
Z is a standard notation for, you know,
X + iy is equal to Z.
So, you can take any
complex
Sorry, any vector, multiply it by any
complex number and it is still some I'm
not going to try to draw it for you.
Uh
stop trying to think about drawing
vectors.
If there is a vector and there's a
complex number, you can multiply them
and it gives you some new vector.
Let's call it uh
Well, let's call it A prime.
So, you can multiply vectors by numbers,
complex numbers.
And that's about it. That That's all
there really is to a vector space. Any
set of objects for which you can do this
is a vector space.
Give you some examples of vector spaces.
If A's and B's are comp- A's
uh
If A's and B's are just real numbers,
then you can add them to make new real
numbers.
But you cannot multiply them by complex
numbers and still expect to get real
numbers.
Okay? You can multiply them by real
numbers and get other real numbers.
So, the real numbers are a real vector
space.
How about the complex numbers? Are the
complex numbers a uh
a complex vector space?
Yes. You can add them
and get new get other complex numbers.
Any two complex numbers you can add and
any complex number you can multiply by
another complex number and get back a
complex number.
So, the complex numbers are the simplest
example of a complex vector space.
Okay?
Let me give you another example of a
complex vector space. This one's
incredibly complicated,
but still pretty easy to write down.
Take any function of a variable. Let's
call it psi of x. Now, x
may be an ordinary real variable,
a function on a line.
Function on a line, but it's a complex
function on a line. It has a real and
imaginary part.
Complex function on a line.
Can you add two functions and get
another function?
Certainly.
So,
functions, just functions, are things
you can add to get other functions.
Can you multiply
a complex function by a complex number
and get a complex function?
Yes.
Take any complex function, multiply it
by a complex number, you get another
complex function.
So, so functions
form a vector space. Now, that's a
complicated idea, and I don't want to
get that complicated yet.
So, let's erase that from the
blackboard.
I'll give you another
vector space.
Another complex vector space.
Let's just
make some symbols.
A bracket
and put in entries
two entries into the bracket. And the
two entries are themselves complex
numbers.
Alpha 1 and Alpha 2.
Alpha equals a complex number.
Both Alpha 1 and Alpha 2. And Alpha 1
and Alpha 2 can be anything.
The collection of such symbols
is also a complex vector space.
Here's the rule.
Supposing you have two of them. Here's
one
and here's another one, beta 1, beta 2.
And you add them. What does that mean?
Definition. The definition of the sum of
two
These are called columns.
The sum of two columns like that is just
to add the entries.
Alpha 1 + beta 1,
alpha 2 + beta 2.
So, given any two
abstract
symbols in which the entries are filled
in with complex numbers, any two of
them, alpha and beta,
we can add them and get a third one.
So,
column vectors like this, little columns
of two entries like this,
satisfy the first rule.
And the second rule
is that if you want to take a column
and multiply it by a complex number, all
you do
is multiply each entry
by the complex number.
You multiply each entry separately,
and then you construct something
which is just z times that.
So, just pairs of complex numbers like
this form a vector space. It's a very
abstract concept, but not very hard.
How about triples of them?
Sure.
All right. So, any length of column like
that. Now, what you don't want to do is
add a column of two to a column of
three. You don't have a rule for that.
All right. So, columns of different
length
form different vector spaces, completely
different abstract vector spaces.
Any question about the meaning
the abstract This is not hard, but it is
abstract.
Are those the only two requirements for
vector space?
Yeah, well, I think it's also important
that there be a zero vector.
Zero vector is the unique vector which,
when you add it to any other vector,
gives back the same the same uh
the same vector.
Right.
I
I didn't feel like writing it down, but
uh Closure requirement. The general
closure requirement, the result be
closed under under what particular
space?
Closed under addition? I think right.
Closed under multiplication by I think
you've illustrated Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, that's right.
Is this the same as matrices?
Is this the same as matrices? Is it
what?
Matrix.
Yeah.
This is a
Usually, the term matrices, in this
class in any case, will be reserved for
square matrices. Square matrices are
collections of uh numbers which form
square arrays, as many rows as columns.
But, the general notion of a matrix can
have
different numbers of rows and columns.
And the vector
would be a matrix with only one column,
in this case, two rows.
So, yes, this would be a special case of
a matrix.
But, um you know, in many contexts, one
reserves the term matrix
for a square matrix. And I will use it
that way. I will use the term matrix to
mean a square matrix.
Uh so, I I didn't want to use that
terminology.
Okay, are
are you thoroughly uh
saturated with abstract mathematics?
This is This is This should be This
should be um straightforward for you.
Okay, now we introduce another
abstraction.
Another abstraction.
Basically,
it's the abstraction of
a comp Given a complex vector space,
the complex conjugate of the vector
space.
The complex conjugate of the vector
space is sort of the space of complex
conjugate vectors. Just like you can
have for any number a complex conjugate,
any uh complex number,
there's a complex conjugate to go with
it.
So, in that sense, the complex number
system
uh has a
a
a dual version, which is the complex
conjugates of the original numbers.
So, do the complex conjugate vector
spaces. And roughly speaking, the
complex conjugate vector space, so the
the dual vector space, usually called
the dual, is roughly speaking the
complex conjugates of the original
vectors. We'll make that more precise as
we go along.
But, what it is is a separate vector
space
whose elements are in one-to-one
correspondence
with the elements of the original vector
space. So, if there is a vector A in the
original space,
Let's write it this way.
Then, there is
a vector in the dual, let's call the
dual vector space, but as I said, it is
more or less the complex conjugate, and
it's written this way.
It's just written as a backward Dirac
symbol.
We'll learn to call these things bra
vectors and these things ket vectors,
but no, this is the ket vector, this is
the bra vector. But, for the moment,
they're just symbols.
Um an example.
If the vector space is just the space of
complex numbers,
then the dual vector space is just the
space of complex conjugates of those
numbers.
Okay.
Okay, so there's a one-to-one
correspondence
between vectors and their complex
conjugates.
Let's uh
write down first some postulates about
the complex conjugate vector space,
and then test it out by seeing if we can
find a concrete representation of the
notion.
Write down some abstract postulates, and
then check, just as we did here. We
said, "Here's a concrete representation
of
the notions that we wrote down over
here."
Let's write down
the abstract
postulates about the dual vector space.
All right. So, first of all,
for any vector,
there is a
dual vector.
And they're in one-to-one
correspondence.
Next.
If you take two vectors
and you add them together,
then
the dual of the sum
is just the sum of the duals.
So, if you take a vector which is made
up out of the sum of two other vectors,
then its reflection in the dual space is
just the sum of the individual dual
vectors.
These are postulates. These are
postulates, if you like,
but they're not so obscure.
The third assumption is that if you take
any vector
and multiply it by a complex conjugate,
sorry, by a by a complex number,
then its reflection in the dual space.
Now, anybody want to guess?
Of course, it involves the dual vector
to A,
but not multiplication by Z,
but multiplication by the complex
conjugate of Z, Z star.
Z star is the complex conjugate of V of
Z.
This would be true of complex numbers.
If you take a complex number and
multiply it by another complex number,
then the complex conjugate of the whole
thing is the product of complex
conjugates. That's all this is saying.
So, we think of the
dual vector space is basically just a
complex conjugate vector space
in some sense.
Okay, let's see if we can make any sense
out of this
in terms of um in terms of these column
vectors here. Question.
Yeah,
is is A + B the same as B + A? Yes. Yes,
A + B is the same as B + A. Good
question. Yes, when you add vectors
and you can see that from here.
I should have All right. I I'm sorry.
Somebody asked me, are there any other
rules about the definition of vector
spaces? And indeed there are. Among
other ones,
uh I this that may be all there is. That
it doesn't matter which order you or you
you add them in.
Yes. But you can see that here.
Uh the sum of two vectors
is just given by numerically adding the
complex numbers here. And of course,
numerical addition of complex numbers
doesn't matter which way you we you
order them.
Good. So, that's a good point.
Okay, so let's come back now
to
Let's put this up on top
and come back to this concrete
non-abstract representation of the
complex
uh vector space.
Here we have a vector.
This object is representing
the vector A.
The one that I erased with beta, that's
representing the vector B. But right
now, I don't need the vector B.
Okay?
What about the object if if this object
represents A,
then what is the object which represents
the dual
vector the dual vector, the
corresponding dual vector? And the
answer is, it's the same pair of numbers
except they're complex conjugates.
The same pair of numbers, not quite.
They're complex conjugates, alpha one
star and alpha two star.
But just to keep track that we're
talking about a different vector space,
we write it
in row form, not as a column, but as a
row. This is just a trick to remember
that this object belongs to the dual
vector space, this object belongs to the
original vector space, and that they're
different.
All right. So, the dual vector space
image
of alpha one and alpha two is alpha one
star alpha two star.
That's the uh
that's the dual vector.
And then you can check. You can check
uh with this definition
are the postulates,
namely that if you add two vectors
and then
take the dual, that whether or not you
get the sum of duals.
And you can check whether when you
multiply this by a complex number and
then mult and then take its dual,
whether it just multiplies by the
complex conjugate number. Answer is yes.
So, just laying out a pair of complex
numbers like this
makes a vector space, and the dual
vector space is the same pair of numbers
except complex conjugated
and laid out in a row. Laid out in a row
just to remember
that it's about the same
creature doesn't live in the same space
of things.
And that's the idea of
uh
a complex vector space.
As I said, again, very abstract and very
easy.
Final concept.
Well, it's not the final concept, but a
the n plus first concept. I'm not sure
what n is.
How many people find this hard?
It's not very hard. How many people find
it familiar?
Quite a lot of people find it familiar.
That's good.
Those who don't find it familiar
apparently didn't find it hard. That's
also good.
The product of two vectors.
The inner product of two vectors. The
inner product of two vectors, it's the
analog of the dot product for pointers.
The analog of the dot product for
pointers.
The inner product between two vectors is
strictly speaking the inner product
between a vector and a vector
and a the dual of a vector.
Given two vectors, let's call them A and
B.
One does not form the product of A with
B, the inner product. Instead,
one takes B
and constructs its image in the dual
vector space.
And then
takes the product
of the vector A with the dual vector B.
In Dirac's language, you take a ket
vector and you multiply it by a bra
vector. And when you do so,
you make a bra ket or a bracket.
The bracket.
The bracket, of course, is this thing
over here. And the two together.
I think this one is called the ket and
this one is called the bra. So, it's a
bra ket.
All right. So, the the inner product of
two vectors
is really
a product of a vector and the dual of a
vector.
Now, is it the same
as multiplying
the bra vector A with the ket vector B?
Question.
Is it the same to multiply the bra B
with the ket A or the bra A with the ket
B? And the answer is no.
The answer is no. It is not the same
operation,
but in fact, they're closely related.
Okay. The part the the axiom We're we're
we're still talking about axioms now.
The axiom is that these two are related
by
complex conjugation.
I complex conjugated A to go from the
from the ket vector to the bra vector.
I complex conjugated B to go from the
bra vector to the ket vector.
So, if this is a product of A, roughly
speaking, times B star, this is the
product of B star times A. This is the
complex conjugate of this.
So,
A another postulate
another axiom of uh
of complex vector spaces
is that the inner product of A
with B
is the complex conjugate of the inner
product of B
with A
star.
So, would that be in in in normal vector
space
language or whatever? Nothing to do with
quantum mechanics per se.
I mean,
there the inner product is just all the
vectors are in the same vector space.
In which in ordinary vector space.
Right. Yes.
But so, this is this this is still
called an inner product even though it's
kind of this special thing with the
complex conjugate. So,
Now, the the usual vector spaces that
you think about are real vector spaces.
And for a real vector space for a real
number, there's no difference between
the number and its complex conjugate.
So,
the real vector space satisfies the same
postulates except it's uh the complex
conjugation is completely a trivial
operation. But I mean, you could have a
vector space where you take the inner
product of two complex vectors and it
doesn't it doesn't involve any
conjugation. You just mult multiply them
component-wise and take the sum, right?
Yes, you could. You could invent such
things. Then, of course, the inner
product of a vector with itself would
not be real.
That's okay. Who cares?
So, you could invent such things. Turns
out not to be terribly useful in the
context of quantum mechanics.
So, you know, it's largely a question of
what's useful.
And what's useful
winds up being this concept.
Right? But yes, you could you could
certainly define such a thing.
Uh
it's not a commonly defined thing.
Doesn't seem to have a lot of use.
This structure occurs over and over in
all kinds of places, not only quantum
mechanics. I mean, this this complex
vector spaces are very very common
things in mathematics.
And uh
Okay, let's check now. Let's see if we
can
postulate a construction
for the inner product
of
the dual vector beta.
All right, remember we when you you
complex conjugate when you take times
the
original vector alpha.
This is supposed to be now
I guess I called it
B
A.
And I haven't all I've didn't written
down the notation for B and the notation
for A.
Column vector for A, row vector for B,
complex conjugated.
All right.
I will tell you now what the rule is.
Again,
we're
making up rules which will satisfy those
postulates up there. And it's a very
simple construction. It's just
beta one star times alpha one plus beta
two star
times alpha two.
In other words, you take the first entry
of the dual vector times the first entry
of the of the
uh of the vector alpha.
Add it to the first entry to the second
entry times the second entry.
So, it's actually just a generalization
of multiplying beta times alpha.
But it's also a generalization of the
dot product.
If you remember about dot products of
ordinary vectors,
you simply take the the sums of the
products of the components.
If you have two pointers and they're
labeled by components,
both of them, then the dot product is
just the sums of the products of the
components.
Does that satisfy the rules up here?
Uh what are what are the rules?
I think I must have erased the rule,
huh?
I did erase the rule. The rule was
um
It's up there. What's the last The last
sentence.
Okay.
What happens if you interchange alpha
and beta
or A and B?
Then this becomes alpha one star alpha
two star
times beta one beta two
if I interchange them, and that's equal
to
alpha one star beta one
plus alpha two star
beta two, and that's just a complex
conjugate of this. It really is the
complex conjugate. So, interchanging
alpha and beta or A and B
really does
interchange
num the value of the product and its
complex conjugate.
That's the notion of a complex vector
space
and an inner product on the complex
vector space.
Now,
let's just take a couple of uh special
cases of inner products.
What about the inner product of a vector
with itself?
Or a vector with its image in the dual
space.
Let's take the inner product of A with
A.
What do I know about that?
Well, first of all, let's let's let's
I'm setting B equal to A.
That tells me that the inner product of
a vector with itself is equal to its own
complex conjugate.
I just substituted for for B
A. The inner product of a vector with
itself is equal to its own
its own complex conjugate. What kind of
number is equal to its own complex
conjugate?
A real number.
So, the inner product of a vector with
itself is always real.
That's pretty obvious just from here. If
I take alpha
and
multiply it
by its image, I get alpha star alpha
plus alpha two star alpha two.
Each one of these is real.
Not only is it real, it's also something
else.
Positive.
Alpha star alpha, a number times its own
complex conjugate is always positive.
So, it's real and positive.
The inner product of a vector with
itself is real and positive.
And it's considered to be the square of
the length of the vector.
The square root of the inner product of
a vector with itself defines the length
of the vector.
So, complex vectors have real lengths.
Real and positive lengths. Also, the
square of the
the um
Both the square and the length itself
are defined to be positive.
Uh so, that's not too obscure.
Every complex vector
has a length which is the square root of
the sums of the squares of its
components, but squares now mean
uh multiply by complex conjugate.
Next notion
important notion, the notion of
orthogonality of vectors.
The notion of orthogonality of vectors
is as we'll see is a very important one.
I'll give some examples in a few
minutes.
The notion of orthogonality
between two vectors
is exactly the same as it is for
ordinary vectors, that the inner product
read dot product if you like, the inner
product is zero.
If the inner product of two vectors is
zero, they are said to be orthogonal.
That defines or perpendicular.
Okay, so two vectors are orthogonal if
the inner product between them is zero.
Let's see if we can make up some
orthogonal vectors. It's very easy.
Oh oh oh.
What about reading What about if I take
the inner product the opposite order?
It's just the complex conjugate of zero.
But the complex conjugate of is zero of
zero is zero.
So,
saying that two vectors are orthogonal,
it doesn't matter which order you put
them in. The notion of orthogonality
doesn't depend on order, although the
general idea of inner product does.
All right. So, now we have the notion of
orthogonal vectors.
In a real vector space,
how do you define the dimensionality of
the real vector space?
Or give me a definition of the
dimensionality. There are many
definitions, of course, but uh
anybody have one?
Yeah, but let's let's work in a more
abstract way without without Yes, that's
of course correct, but uh
The maximal number of orthogonal vectors
that you can find in the space.
Okay? So, if the vector space is
two-dimensional, ordinary
two-dimensional vector space, there are
two mutually orthogonal vectors. You
cannot find a third vector which is
orthogonal to both of them.
Right? So, the maximal number of
mutually orthogonal vectors in three
dimensions, where's my
I've got three mutually orthogonal
vectors. Now, of course, there are many
sets of three mutually orthogonal
vectors, but given three, I cannot find
a fourth one.
All right. So, a three-dimensional
vector space has a maximal number of
three mutually orthogonal vectors.
And the same is true or the same
definition That's definition is true for
a complex
vector space.
The maximal number of orthogonal vectors
that you can find
is equal to the dimensionality of the
space.
It does correspond to the number of
entries here, the number of components.
It is the same and you can prove that.
It's a little exercise.
Prove that the number of components of
the vector is the same as the number of
mutually orthogonal vectors.
But let's just talk let's just
Are there any uh mutually orthogonal
vectors we can write down? Sure, loads
and loads of them. But a very simple
case would be 1 0.
Now, 1 and 0 are 1 and 0 complex
numbers?
Well, yeah, real numbers are special
cases of complex numbers.
So, a real uh complex number can be
real.
Here's one.
And here's another one.
Uh 0 1.
This one has a 1 in the first place, it
has a 0 in the first place. This one has
a 0 in the
You you get the idea.
The inner product is 0 * 1 + 1 * 0.
Okay? So, the two vectors
or
let's let's just write it in terms of
column vectors.
1 0 and 0 1. 1 0 and 0 1 are orthogonal
vectors.
The inner product of this one with the
dual of this one is 0.
Right? That's because 1 * 0 + 0 * 1
is just 0.
All right, so there are plenty of
orthogonal vectors around.
But
in two dimensions, and this is two
dimensions, once you found two of them,
you cannot find a third. So, there's a
little exercise.
Prove that there can be no vector which
is both orthogonal to this and
orthogonal to that.
That's not hard to do. That's very easy
to do.
Hm? Oh oh oh oh.
Yeah.
Yeah. 0 0 is always orthogonal to
everything. Right? Yeah.
Yeah. Uh right. So, one should be
careful and say
the maximal number of non-zero
orthogonal mutually orthogonal vectors.
Good point.
Right?
Okay. Um
that's a mathematical interlude for
tonight.
Complex vector spaces.
And the next time we will discuss how
the space of states and what it means
for the space of states of these simple
qubits to be two-dimensional vector
spaces.
Very very different than saying that
they consist of points in a set.
The space of states is, in fact, a
vector space. And then try to make
contact with the mathematics of vector
spaces and the strange things that are
happening or that seem to be happening
here with these uh these um
uh
these funny properties of measurements.
That's where we want to go.
So, we've done some physics, some
experimental physics on this blackboard
up there. And we've done some abstract
mathematics over here. And next time we
want to connect them and show what the
what the abstract mathematics how it
represents or how it can be used to
represent this unusual kind of uh
uh logic of qubits.
If we strictly look at the patterns, is
it going to be meaningful to
define a multiplication operation where
we create a 2 by 2 matrix
which would be beta 1 star alpha 1, beta
1 star alpha 1?
You're asking
I I I I
Yes. The answer is yes. Yes, absolutely.
We'll construct inner products, outer
products, uh all sorts of products.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's right.
The outer product of two matrix of two
vectors is a matrix.
Yeah.
And of course, how do you represent it
uh I just
Well.
The outer product of two vectors
is represented this way.
And it it is a matrix, but we'll come to
that.
All the postulates apply to a vector
space of functions, for example, as
well. But that was it is less obvious
than
Yeah.
A vector space of functions can be
thought of
as a column vectors,
but ins- but where the entries are
continuous.
So, we have alpha. Alpha is the
function. And alpha of the first
entry, alpha of the second entry,
instead of that, we have a continuous
family of alphas. Alpha evaluated at
point x1, alpha evaluated at point x2,
alpha evaluated at point x3. And of
course, we can't really write it as a
literally as a as a um
as a uh discrete collection like that.
But if you like,
think of these alphas here, alpha 1 and
alpha 2, as just a function of two
variables a function
of an entry 1 and 2.
Instead of a function of x, it's a
function of a variable which is either 1
or 2.
So, yes, complex functions form
complex vector spaces.
The inner product we will we will
discuss that.
Back on the upper left
where you have that apparatus turned at
angle theta.
If you consider the sequence of
inputs going to outputs, the proportion
of -1s to 1s would be given by cosine
theta.
Is there anything interesting about the
distribution of the -1s within the 1s?
What does that mean? Well, like higher
order statistics, maybe.
Still, what does that mean? Oh oh oh.
They're just completely random.
Completely random. Yeah, just a
completely random variables.
You're talking about the relationship
between the different uh
replications.
A whole bunch of spins and you subject
them all to the same. And the question
is you're I think you're asking whether
there are correlations between them. No.
No, they're completely independent,
uncorrelated uh
variables.
So, it's still with the qubit experiment
there. Um
Does it make sense to say that when you
when you're measuring the qubit, uh
you're you're you're affecting it, so
you're actually preparing it in a new
state. Yes yes yes yes. That's exactly
right.
you the first time does some something
and the second time it just keeps to
that.
And that's a big difference between
classical mechanics and quantum
mechanics.
In classical mechanics, you can measure
something sufficiently gently to not
affect it, to not disturb it.
In quantum mechanics, whenever you
measure something, you always disturb
it.
So, this is an example of how measuring
something disturbs it and puts it into a
new state.
And I'd say that's a good point. Yes.
Okay.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.